片名:
X战警:最后战役
葛蕾宅
二十年前
我实在不懂,你不能
用超能力让他们同意吗?
I still don't know why I'm here.
Couldn't you just make them say yes?
可以,但那不是我的方法
Yes, I could, but it's not my way.
你该明白
我反对滥用超能力
And I would expect you, of all people, would
understand my feelings on misuse of power.
权力腐化人心
又来了,好,我知道
Ah, power corrupts and all that.
Yes, I know, Charles.
-你何时才会停止说教?
-等到你把话听进去为止
- When are you going to stop lecturing me?
- When you start listening.
我要你来是因为我需要你
You're here because I need you.
我们不用
个别拜访所有学生吧?
We don't have to meet
every one of them in person?
不用,但这个很特别
No. This one's special.
X学校
-很美的校园,老公,你觉得呢?
-册子印刷得很好
What a beautiful campus.
John, don't you think?
Yeah, the brochure is great.
不过琴呢?她的病怎么办?
But what about Jean?
What about her illness?
病?
- lllness?
- John.
你认为你女儿有病?
You think your daughter is sick, Mr. Grey?
也许该让我们单独跟她谈谈
Perhaps it would be best
if we were to speak to her. Alone.
当然
Of course.
琴?你能下来吗?
Jean, can you come down, dear?
那就交给你们了
We'll leave you, then.
未经允许就擅自读心
是很失礼的
It's very rude to read my thoughts,
or Mr. Lensherr's, without our permission.
你以为你是独一无二的?
Did you think you were
the only one of your kind, young lady?
我们是变种人,我们跟你一样
We're mutants, Jean. We're like you.
真的?我很怀疑
Really? I doubt that.
Oh, Charles.
查而斯
我喜欢这孩子
I like this one.
你拥有比你想像中更强的力量
问题是,你能控制它吗?
You have more power
than you can imagine, Jean.
The question is, will you control that power?
还是你会被它控制?
Or let it control you?
十年前
华伦?
儿子?你还好吧?
Warren? Son, is everything all right?
-怎么回事?
-没事,我马上出去
- What's going on?
- Nothing. I'll be right out.
你已经在里面超过一个小时了
Come on.
You've been in there for over an hour.
快开门,华伦?
Open the door. Warren.
等一下
One second!
快开门
Open this door.
Warren.
华伦?让我进去,快开门
Let me in there right now. Open the door.
老天爷
Oh, God.
-这怎么可能
-爸,对不起
- Not you.
- Dad, I'm sorry.
不远的未来
世界即将毁灭
你们却还坐在这里?
The whole world's going to hell
and you're just going to sit there? Let's go.
巴比
Bobby!
谢了,幻影猫
Thanks, Kitty.
-我们快玩完了
-他们还没准备好
- We're getting killed out here.
- Yeah, I know. They're not ready, Storm.
-罗根！
-别碎碎念
- Logan.
- Oh, don't get your panties in a bunch.
那是我最后一根雪茄
That was my last cigar.
Logan.
-罗根,它逼近了
-继续行动
- It's getting closer.
- Come on. Let's keep moving.
钢人,过来
Hey, Tin Man. Come here.
-你的手臂有力吗?
-罗根,我们要团队合作
- How's your throwing arm?
- Logan, we work as a team.
祝你合作愉快
把我扔过去,就是现在
Yeah. Good luck with that. Throw me. Now.
罗根,别这么做
Dammit, Logan, don't do this.
下课
Class dismissed.
钢人,扔的好
Hey, Colossus. Nice throw.
模拟结束
Simulation complete.
-那算什么?
-危机模拟课
- What was that?
- Danger room session.
-你知道我在说什么
-别紧张嘛
- You know what I mean.
- Lighten up.
-别乱改规矩,我在设法教他们
-我是教了他们东西
You can't change the rules.
I'm trying to teach 'em something.
那应该是防守练习
- I taught 'em something.
- It was a defensive exercise.
攻击是最佳防守
还是倒过来说?
Yeah, best defense is a good offence.
Or is it the other way round?
-这不是游戏
-你还真是唬倒我了
- This isn't a game, Logan.
- Well, you sure fooled me.
我是代课老师
有问题找史考特
Hey, I'm just a sub.
You got a problem, talk to Scott.
-史考特
-琴
- Scott!
- Jean.
我需要你,史考特
史考特、史考特
Scott. Scott.
Scott.
-你还好吧?
-我很好
- Are you OK?
- I'm fine.
你看起来不大好,你在躲我
You seem like you're avoiding me.
Something's wrong.
除了我碰男友他就会死
之外都好
I can't touch my boyfriend without
killing him. Other than that I'm wonderful.
我有给过你压力吗?
Hey. I don't think that's fair.
Have I ever put any pressure on you?
你是男人,你想的只有一件事
You're a guy, Bobby.
Your mind's only on one thing.
-大家都在找你,你没现身
-你在乎什么?
- They were looking for you. You didn't show.
- What do you care?
-我得掩护你
-我没请你掩护
- For starters, I had to cover your ass.
- I didn't ask you to.
你是没有,教授有
No, you didn't. The professor did.
-我只是过来看看
-看过就走吧,罗根
- I was just passing through.
- So pass through, Logan.
听着
Hey, look.
-我知道你的感觉,当琴...
-别说了
- I know how you feel. When Jean died...
- Don't.
我们该继续活下去
Maybe it's time for us to move on.
我不像你能愈合得那么快
Not everybody heals as fast as you, Logan.
变种人事务部
美国科学杂志
『追踪变种人』
部长先生?
- Mr. Secretary.
- Yes.
-会议已经开始了
-谢谢
- The meeting's begun, sir.
- Thank you.
美国总统
总统先生?
Mr. President.
坐,老亨
Have a seat, Hank.
国土安全部
之前追踪万磁王
Homeland Security was tracking Magneto.
里斯本、日内瓦、蒙特娄
We got hits in Lisbon, Geneva, Montreal.
卫星追丢了,不过却逮到二奖
NAVSAT lost him crossing the border,
but we did get a consolation prize.
我们逮到她
闯入食品药物管理局
We picked her up breaking into the FDA.
知道她模仿谁吗?
崔思克部长
You know who she's been imitating?
Secretary Trask here.
是啊,她做得到
Yes, sir. She can do that.
-到此为止,我们逮到她了
-你的监狱关不住她
- Not any more, she can't. We got her.
- You think your prisons can hold her?
我们有新式监狱
随时移动,制敌机先
We have some new prisons.
We'll keep them mobile. Be a step ahead.
万磁王人呢?
Where is Magneto?
瑞雯?
Raven?
-瑞雯,我问你问题
-我不回应我的奴隶名
- Raven, I asked you a question.
- I don't answer to my slave name.
瑞雯达克霍,那是你的真名
Raven Darkholme.
That's your real name, isn't it?
或者他说服你,你没有家人?
Or has he convinced you
you don't have a family any more?
我的家人想杀我,你这个烂人
My family tried to kill me,
you pathetic meat sack.
好,那么,魔形女
他在哪里?
OK, then. Mystique - where is he?
在这里跟我们一起
In here with us.
我不想玩游戏,我要答案
I don't want to play games with you.
I want answers.
你不想玩游戏?
You don't want to play games with me?
给我住手,说,万磁王在哪?
You are going to stop this.
Tell me, where is Magneto?
要知道他人在哪里?
You wanna know where he is?
臭人类！
Homo sapien.
她被捕只会激怒万磁王
不过有了她,我们就有胜算
You know, her capture
will only provoke Magneto,
but having her does give us
some diplomatic leverage.
基于原则
我不能跟这些人协商
On principle, I can't negotiate
with these people.
-那不就是你指派我的原因吗?
-是的
- I thought that's why you appointed me, sir.
- Yes, it is.
-不过那不是你召我来的原因
-不是,这才是
- But that's not why you called me here.
- No. This is.
这是她从食品药物管理局偷的
It's what she stole from the FDA.
沃辛实验室
抑制变种人基因
老天爷
Dear Lord.
-这可行吗?
-我们相信可行
- Is it viable?
- We believe it is.
你明白
这对变种人会有多大冲击
You realize the impact
this'll have on the mutant community?
我明白,所以我们现在
需要你的外交手腕
Yes. I do. That's precisely why
we need some of your diplomacy now.
当一个个体具备超能力
运用或误用就会影响一切
When an individual acquires great power,
the use or misuse of that power is everything.
是为整体福祉?
或是为个人私利或毁灭世界?
Will it be for the greater good or will it
be used for personal or for destructive ends?
我们必须自问这个问题
为什么
Now, this is a question
we must all ask ourselves.
Why? Because we are mutants.
因为我们是变种人
就心灵而言,这代表某种问题
For psychics,
this presents a particular problem.
何时能运用我们的能力
以及我们何时会跨越误用的界限
When is it acceptable to use our power
and when do we cross that invisible line
使我们变成暴君
that turns us into tyrants
over our fellow man?
但爱因斯坦说道德规范是
人类的事,与超自然力量无关
But Einstein said that ethics
are an exclusive human concern
without any superhuman authority behind it.
就我们所知
爱因斯坦并不是变种人
Einstein wasn't a mutant so far as we know.
莫拉博士寄给我一份研究报告
This case study was sent to me
by a colleague, Dr. Moira McTaggert. Jones.
这个人出生时没有高阶的脑力
The man you see here was born
with no higher-level brain functions.
器官神经系统正常
但他毫无意识
His organs and nervous system work,
but he has no consciousness to speak of.
若我们移转一个有四个孩子的
What if we were to transfer
the consciousness of one person,
...罹癌父亲的意识进去会怎样?
say a father of four with terminal cancer,
into the body of this man?
我们该如何决定什么是
合乎道德规范的行止,什么是...
How are we to decide what falls within
the range of ethical behavior and what...
教授?
Professor?
我们明天再继续上
下课
We'll continue this tomorrow.
Class dismissed.
预报说今天晴空万里
The forecast was for sunny skies.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我不用读心
也知道你心里有事
I don't have to be psychic
to see that something's bothering you.
万磁王成逃犯,内阁有变种人
I don't understand. Magneto's a fugitive,
总统又善良,我们为何还要躲?
we've a mutant in the cabinet,
a president who understands us - why hide?
我们没躲
我们还是有敌人,我得保护学生
We're not hiding. But we still have enemies.
I must protect my students. You know that.
对
不过我们不能永远当学生
Yes, but we can't be students forever.
暴风女
我早就不把你们当学生了
Storm, I haven't thought of you
as my student for years.
事实上
我想你有一天能取代我
In fact, I thought that perhaps
you might take my place some day.
-不过史考特...
-史考特变了
- But Scott's...
- Scott's a changed man.
琴的死让他发狂
He took Jean's death so hard.
对,情况有好转
Yes, things are better out there,
不过你们知道
世事如天气般多变
but you, of all people,
know how fast the weather can change.
你有事没告诉我们
There's something you're not telling us.
老亨
Hank?
查而斯
Ororo. Charles.
我喜欢你的新发型
I love what you've done with your hair.
你也一样
谢谢你愿意见我
You too. Thank you for seeing me
on such short notice.
随时欢迎,你是这里的一份子
Henry, you are always welcome here.
You're a part of this place.
-我有消息
-跟艾瑞克有关?
- I have news.
- Is it Eric?
没,但有进展
No. Though we have been making
some progress on that front.
-魔形女已被捕
-这毛球是谁啊?
- Mystique was recently apprehended.
- Who's the fur ball?
-亨利麦寇,变种人事务部长
-是啊,部长,西装不错
Hank McCoy. Secretary of Mutant Affairs.
Right, right. The secretary. Nice suit.
-亨利,这是罗根,他是...
-金钢狼
- Henry, this is Logan. He's...
- Wolverine.
-听说你像野兽般勇猛
-瞧瞧说话的是谁啊
- I hear you're quite an animal.
- Look who's talking.
-万磁王会来救魔形女
-他不是问题
Magneto's gonna come get Mystique.
至少不是最迫切的
Magneto's not the problem.
At least not our most pressing one.
有家制药公司研发出变种抗体
可以压抑变种基因
A major pharmaceutical company
has developed a mutant antibody.
A way to suppress the mutant X gene.
-压抑?
-永久有效
- Suppress?
- Permanently.
医生称之为解药
They're calling it a cure.
太可笑了,你不能治愈变种人
That's ridiculous.
You can't cure being a mutant.
-从科学上来说...
-我们何时成了一种疾病了?
- Scientifically speaking...
- When did we become a disease?
Storm.
暴风女
他们正在宣布
They're announcing it now.
这些变种人是人,跟我们一样
These so-called mutants
are people just like us.
他们感染到的只是一种疾病
影响了健康的细胞活动
Their affliction is nothing more
than a disease,
a corruption of healthy cellular activity.
不过我在此宣布
你们会有希望
But I stand here today
to tell you that there's hope.
这里曾经是世上最知名的监狱
This site, once the world's
most famous prison,
现在将成为解放变种人的基地
will now be the source of freedom
for all mutants who choose it.
各位女士先生
我在此呈现变种的解决方式
Ladies and gentlemen...
I proudly present the answer to mutation.
我们终于有了治疗的针剂
Finally, we have a cure.
谁想治疗?
懦夫才会想融入人群
Who would want this cure? I mean, what
kind of coward would take it just to fit in?
拯救受迫害的人算懦夫吗?
Is it cowardice to save oneself
from persecution?
融入人群不容易
Not all of us can fit in so easily.
-你又不会掉毛
-这可能是政府主导的
- You don't shed on the furniture.
- The government probably cooked this up.
-他们与此毫无关系
-那句话我以前就听说过了
- The government had nothing to do with it.
- I've heard that before.
孩子,我在你有爪子之前
就为变种人奋斗
My boy, I have been fighting for mutant rights
since before you had claws.
-他叫我孩子?
-是真的吗?他们能治好我们?
- Did he just call me boy?
- Is it true? They can cure us?
是啊,看来是真的
Yes, Rogue. It appears to be true.
不,教授
No. Professor.
他们无法治愈我们
They can't cure us.
知道原因吗?因为没有需要
不只是你
You wanna know why? Because there's
nothing to cure. Nothing's wrong with you.
所有变种人都没问题
Or any of us, for that matter.
社区行动会议
人类勿入
How should we, as mutants, respond?
Here's what I think.
变种人该怎么回应?
我们要组织起来
将我们的抗议传达给正确的人
This is about getting organized.
Bringing our complaints to the right people.
我们要组织委员会跟政府对话
We need to put together a committee
and talk to the government.
他们不了解变种人,不懂得
我们有什么特别
They don't understand. They don't know
what it means to be a mutant.
我们要展现给他们看、教育他们
让他们知道我们会继续存在
We need to show them, educate them,
let them know that we're here to stay.
听我说
他们不会认真对待我们,除非...
People, you must listen.
They won't take us seriously...
-他们想灭绝我们
-治疗是自愿的
- They wanna exterminate us.
- This cure is voluntary.
-没人说要灭绝
-根本没人提过这点
Nobody is talking about extermination.
No one ever talks about it.
他们直接付诸行动
They just do it.
你们要是继续忽视这些征兆
And you'll go on with your lives
ignoring the signs all around you.
有一天,空气静止、黑夜降临
他们就会找上你们
And then one day, when the air is still
and the night has fallen, they come for you.
你们要明白
当你们还在组织时
Then you realize, while you're talking
about organizing and committees,
灭绝行动已然展开,不会错的
the extermination has already begun.
他们会先展开攻击
Make no mistake, my brothers.
They will draw first blood.
他们会强迫我们接受治疗
They will force their cure upon us.
问题是
你们要加入我们一起奋战
The only question is,
will you join my brotherhood and fight?
还是要坐以待毙?
Or wait for the inevitable genocide?
你们要站在哪一边?人类?
Who will you stand with? The humans?
还是我们?
Or us?
你这穿着怪披风
撂狠话的家伙
You talk pretty tough for a guy in a cape.
退开
Back off.
你很自傲是变种人,你的记号呢
If you're so proud of being a mutant,
where's your mark?
我向你保证,我曾被做过记号
I have been marked once, my dear.
Let me assure you.
不准任何针头再碰触我的皮肤
No needle shall ever touch my skin again.
你知道你在跟谁说话吗?
You know who you're talking to?
你呢?
Do you?
你有啥能耐?
And what can you do?
你很有天份吗?
So you have talents?
此外还有其他东西
我知道你能控制金属品
That and more. I know you control metal.
还有,这里有87个变种人
这么多人之中
And I know there's 87 mutants in here,
none above a class three.
只有你们两个高于第三级
Other than you two.
你能感测到其他变种人的能力?
You can sense other mutants
and their powers?
你能为我找出其中一位吗?
Could you locate one for me?
让我出去！我命令你释放我
Let me out of here.
I demand that you release me.
知道我是谁吗?我是美国总统
Do you know who I am?
I'm the president of the United States.
总统?
Oh, Mr. President.
给我闭嘴！
Shut up.
你为什么要这么对我?放我下来
我是个好女孩,求你,放我走
Why are you doing this to me? Let me down.
I'll be a good girl. Please let me go.
求求你
Please.
再继续这样
我会赏你一脸喷雾,贱人
Keep it up. I'll spray you in the face, bitch.
等我出去
我要亲手宰了你
When I get out of here,
I'm going to kill you myself.
是啊
Yeah, right.
-麦寇部长,欢迎莅临沃辛实验室
-谢谢,这里不太容易来
Secretary McCoy,
welcome to Worthington Labs.
Thank you, Dr. Rao.
Not an easy place to get to.
这是最安全的地点
所以我们才将治疗资源放这
It's the safest location we could find. That's
why we keep the source of the cure here.
他是变种人,你明白我们的立场
He is a mutant. You understand our concern.
-我们完全遵守贵部政策
-他要待在这里多久?
- We are in compliance with your policy.
- How long will you keep the boy here?
直到将他的DNA定位
我们能复制,却无法重制
Until we can fully map his DNA.
We can replicate it, but we can't generate it.
他有什么能力?
And his power? What is its range?
你会看到的
You'll see.
吉米?
Jimmy.
我想让你见一个人
There's someone I would like you to meet.
你好,孩子
Hello there, son.
-嗨
-我叫亨利麦寇
- Hi.
- My name is Hank McCoy.
对不起
I'm sorry.
没关系
It's OK.
你有惊人的天赋
谢谢你,吉米
You have an amazing gift. Thank you, Jimmy.
很特别,不是吗?
Extraordinary, isn't he?
是啊
Yes, he is.
Scott.
史考特?史考特?
-你听得见我吗?我还在这里
-停
- Can you hear me? I'm still here. Scott.
- Stop.
-我在这里
-停！
- I'm here. Scott. Scott.
- Stop it.
- Scott. Scott.
史考特
I need you, Scott. Scott. Scott.
-停！琴?
-史考特?
Stop!
Jean?
Scott.
怎么会?
How?
我不知道
I don't know.
我想看你的眼睛
I wanna see your eyes.
把这拿掉
- Take these off.
- No.
No.
-不
-相信我,我现在能控制它了
Trust me. I can control it now.
张开眼睛
你伤害不了我
Open them. You can't hurt me.
史考特、史考特
-怎么回事?
-毫无头绪
- What happened?
- No clue.
-教授,你还好吧?
-快去阿卡利湖
- Professor, are you OK?
- Get to Alkali Lake.
-你不想来的
-你想吗?
- You don't want to be here.
- Do you?
我什么都看不到
I can't see a damn thing.
这我可以搞定
I can take care of that.
搞什么?
What the...
Logan!
罗根
她还活着
She's alive.
琴?
Jean.
卷走琴的那股大水
照理应该完全消灭了她
The sheer mass of water that collapsed
on top of Jean should have obliterated her.
她活命的唯一解释是
她的心灵能量形成防护罩
The only explanation of Jean's survival
is that her powers wrapped her
in a cocoon of telekinetic energy.
她会好吗?
Is she gonna be OK?
琴是我遇过唯一的
第五级变种人,她的潜力几近无穷
Jean Grey is the only class five mutant
I've ever encountered, her potential limitless.
她的能力深植于她的潜意识
那是很危险的
Her mutation is seated in the unconscious
part of her mind and therein lay the danger.
她小时候,我制造了心灵围栏
When she was a girl,
I created a series of psychic barriers
将她能力隔绝于理性之外
结果她发展出双重人格
to isolate her powers
from her conscious mind.
-什么意思?
-理性的琴
- Jean developed a dual personality.
- What?
她的能力受到控制
而冬眠的另一边
The conscious Jean, whose powers were
always in her control, and the dormant side.
是一种我们在课堂上称为
┌火凤凰」的个性
A personality that, in our sessions,
came to call itself the Phoenix.
纯粹本能的动物
只为欲望、享乐和愤怒所驱使
A purely instinctual creature,
all desire and joy and rage.
-她知道这些吗?
-她了解多少并不清楚
- She knew all this?
- It's unclear how much she knew.
更重要的是
眼前是我们熟悉的琴
Far more critical is whether the woman
in front of us is the Jean Grey we know,
...还是想挣脱枷锁
的愤怒火凤凰
or the Phoenix furiously struggling to be free.
-她看起来很平和
-我在让她保持平和
- She looks peaceful to me.
- I'm keeping her that way.
我想恢复心灵围栏
困住怪兽
I'm trying to restore the psychic blocks
and cage the beast again.
-你对她做了什么?
-你得明白...
What have you done to her?
-你说的是琴的心灵
-她必须受到控制
- You have to understand...
- You're talking about a person's mind.
- She has to be controlled.
- Controlled?
有时困住怪兽
怪兽反而更生气
Sometimes, when you cage the beast,
the beast gets angry.
你不明白她的能力有多恐怖
You have no idea.
You have no idea of what she is capable.
不,我不明白你有多恐怖
No, Professor.
I had no idea what you were capable of.
这很艰难,但我做了选择
I had a terrible choice to make.
I chose the lesser of two evils.
听起来琴根本就毫无选择
It sounds to me like Jean had no choice at all.
我不用为自已辩护
至少对你不用
I don't have to explain myself,
least of all to you.
历史即将被创造,随着变种疗方
全面上市
History will be made here today.
For the first time,
the so-called mutant cure
will be available to the public.
变种人各界都有强烈反应
Reaction has run the gamut
with mutants on both sides of the line.
有些急欲施打此疗方
其他则激烈反对它的存在
Some are desperate for this cure while others
are offended by the very idea of it.
麦寇部长会有问题吗?
Will Secretary McCoy be a problem?
很难说,他的政治观点
似乎与他个人冲突
Hard to say. His political views seem
somewhat at odds with his personal issues.
抱歉,您的公子来了
Excuse me, sir. Your son's arrived.
好,让他进来
Good. Bring him in.
-你确定要从他开始?
-我想这很重要
Are you sure you want to start with him?
I think it's important. Yes.
-你好,华伦
-你好吗,儿子?
- Hello, Warren.
- How are you, son?
睡得好吗?
- Did you sleep well?
- Yeah.
你这么做我很骄傲
You know, I'm proud of you for doing this.
一切都不会有问题的
我保证
Everything's gonna be fine. I promise.
准备好了?
You ready?
转变时会有点不舒服
The transformation can be a little jarring.
-爸,我们能谈谈吗?
-我们谈过了,一切很快就会结束
- Dad, can we talk about this for a second?
- We've talked about it, son.
It'll all be over soon.
-不会有问题的
-等等,我做不到
- Everything's going to be fine.
- Wait. I can't do this.
华伦,冷静点
Warren, calm down.
-我做不到
-你可以的
- I can't do this.
- Yes, you can.
放轻松就好
- I can't do this.
- Just relax, son. Take it easy. Calm down.
-我保证不会有问题！放轻松！
-爸
- I promise you it will be fine. Warren, relax.
- Dad.
华伦,人生会更美好
Warren, it's a better life.
那是我们都想要的
- It's what we all want.
- No.
不,那是你想要的
It's what you want.
Warren, no!
我早说过了
Told you so.
也该是时候了
About time.
我很忙
找到你要找的东西了?
I've been busy.
Did you find what you were looking for?
源头是
在沃辛实验室的变种小孩
The source of the cure is a mutant.
A child at Worthington Labs.
没有他,他们就没得玩了
Without him, they have nothing.
念出房客名单
Read off the guest list.
41205号:分身人
"Cell 41205. James Madrox."
他在同一时间...
This one robbed seven banks.
-抢了七间银行
-我用得上你这种人
- At the same time.
- I could use a man of your talents.
-我加入
-欢迎加入我们
- I'm in.
- Welcome to the Brotherhood.
-这个要小心
-凯因马可,单独监禁
- Careful with this one.
- "Cain Marko. Solitary confinement."
听听这个
┌囚犯必须全身受限」
Check this out.
"Prisoner must be confined at all times."
他若得到动力,势不可挡
"lf he builds any momentum,
no object can stop him."
真迷人
How fascinating.
-他们叫你什么?
-红坦克
- What do they call you?
- Juggernaut.
-我不明白
-放我出去,我要尿尿
- I can't imagine why.
- Are you going to let me out? I need a pee.
-不错的头盔
-让我的脸更有帅劲
- Nice helmet.
- Keeps my face pretty.
他能让我们的军队更声势浩大
I think he'll make a fine addition to our army.
No!
你救了我
You saved me.
Eric.
抱歉,亲爱的
I'm sorry, my dear.
你已经不是我们的一员了
You're not one of us any more.
真可惜,她本来很美的
Such a shame. She was so beautiful.
-你以为辞职可以影响政策?
-政策未经我同意就制定了
Think resigning will make a difference?
That's no way to influence policy.
Policy is being made without me,
Mr. President.
未经我同意就用治疗剂当武器
The decision to turn the cure into a weapon
was made without me.
行动监狱的意外不可原谅,而你
What happened on that convoy
was inexcusable. But your actions...
老亨,那是单一事件
那些变种人很危险
That was an isolated incident. You have to
understand those mutants were a real threat.
你这是游走在钢索之上
Have you even begun to think
what a slippery slope you're on?
我知道
I have.
我担心当某个人能用心志移动
整个城市时,民主将荡然无存
And I worry about how democracy survives
when one man can move cities with his mind.
我也一样
As do l.
我们都知道情况只会变得更糟
You and I know
that it's only going to get worse.
我也更该要待在我所属的地方
All the more reason
why I need to be where I belong.
Jean.
-你好
-欢迎回来
- Hi, Logan.
- Welcome back.
回到我们初次见面的地方
只不过你我的位置互换
Back where we first met. Only I was
in your place and you were in mine.
你还好吧?
Are you OK?
还好
Yeah.
比还好更好
More than OK.
你让我很不好意思
Logan, you're making me blush.
-你在读我的心?
-我根本不用读
- You're reading my thoughts?
- I don't have to.
没关系
It's OK.
没关系的
-等等
-不
- Wait.
- No.
Jean.
-琴,这不是你
-是的,这是我
- This isn't you.
- Yes, it is me.
也许你该放轻松点
No. Maybe you ought to take it easy.
教授说
你可能会有点不一样
The professor said you might be different.
他最了解了,对不对?
He would know, wouldn't he?
怎么?
你想他没在你脑子里动手脚?
What? You think he's not in your head too?
看看你,罗根
他驯服了你
Look at you, Logan. He's tamed you.
史考特人呢?
Where's Scott?
Jean?
-我在哪里?
-在基地里
- Where am l?
- You're in the mansion.
你得告诉我史考特怎么了
You need to tell me what happened to Scott.
琴,他怎么了?
Jean, tell me what happened to him.
天哪
Oh, God.
看着我
Look at me.
专心看着我
Stay with me. Talk to me.
看着我
- Look at me. Look at me.
- No.
专心,琴
Focus. Focus, Jean.
杀了我
Kill me.
-什么?
-在我继续杀人之前杀了我
- What?
- Kill me before I kill someone else.
-别说那种话
-拜托
- Don't say that.
- Please.
-别说了
-杀了我
- Stop it.
- Kill me.
别说了,看着我,琴
Stop it. Look at me. Look at me. Jean.
不会有事的,我们可以帮你
It'll be all right. We can help you.
教授可以帮你,他能修正一切
Hey. The professor can help. He can fix it.
我不想被修正
I don't want to fix it.
自愿?他们把治愈剂放入枪里
Voluntary? They put the cure in a gun.
我说过他们会先展开攻击
I told you they would draw first blood.
我们怎么办?
- So what do we do?
- What do we do?
我们用这武器当避雷针
吸引更多的志士
We use this weapon as a lightning rod
to bring countless more to our cause.
来吧,我们要建立一支军队
Come. We have an army to build.
我侦测到东西
一股电磁力,庞大无比
I picked something up.
An electromagnetic force. It's massive.
是变种人
It's a mutant.
第五级,是我感受过最强大的
Class five.
More powerful than anything I've ever felt.
比你还强
More powerful than you.
她在哪里?
Where is she?
Logan.
-发生什么事了?
-你做了什么?
- Jean. Jean.
- What happened?
What have you done?
-我想她杀了史考特
-什么?
- I think she killed Scott.
- What?
-那是不可能的
-我警告过你
- That's not possible.
- I warned you.
她离开了,她想阻挡我的侦测
她好强
She's left the mansion, but she's trying
to block my thoughts. She's so strong.
可能太迟了
It may be too late.
葛蕾家
-在这里等我
-什么?
- Wait for me here.
- What?
我要单独去见琴
I need to see Jean alone.
你说的很对
You were right, Charles.
-这一个很特别
-你来这里做什么?
- This one is special.
- What the hell are you doing here?
跟查而斯一样
拜访一个老朋友
Same as the professor. Visiting an old friend.
-我不想惹事生非
-我也不想
- I don't want trouble here.
- Nor do l.
我们进去吧?
So, shall we go inside?
-我来带琴回家,别妨碍我
-就跟以前一样
I came to bring Jean home. Don't interfere.
她需要帮忙,琴病了
- Just like old times, eh?
- She needs help. Jean is not well.
真好笑,你的口气就像她父母
Funny, you sound just like her parents.
不准任何人进来
Nobody gets inside.
-我就知道你会来
-我来带你回家
- I knew you'd come.
- Of course. I've come to bring you home.
-我没有家
-你有的,你有家也有家人
- I have no home.
- Yes, you do. You have a home and a family.
他认为你无法控制你的力量
You know he thinks your power
is too great for you to control.
我不认为
你的心灵游戏这回有用
I don't believe your mind games
are going to work any more, Charles.
你想控制我?
- So you want to control me?
- He does.
-不是的
-他想
我想帮助你
No. I want to help you.
帮助我?我有什么问题?
Help me? What's wrong with me?
-绝对没问题
-艾瑞克！
- Absolutely nothing.
- Eric, stop.
不,查而斯,你总是阻碍她
No, Charles, not this time.
You've always held her back.
为你自已好
For your own good, Jean.
滚出我的脑袋
Stay out of my head.
-我要进去
-教授说他能解决
- I'm going in.
- The professor said he'd handle this.
看着我,琴
我能帮助你,看着我
Look at me, Jean. I can help you. Look at me.
滚出我的脑袋
Get out of my head.
-也许你该听她的话
-你这是危及你自已和所有人
- Perhaps you should listen to her, Charles.
- Trust me. You're a danger to everyone.
-我能帮你
-你想让她打治疗剂
- But I can help you.
- I think you want to give her the cure.
看看史考特出了什么事
你控制不了自已,杀了你爱的人
Look at Scott. You killed the man you loved
because you couldn't control your power.
住口！
No! Stop it!
够了
That's it.
琴,让我进去
不,琴！
Jean, let me in.
No, Jean.
Jean!
别让它控制你
Don't let it control you.
查而斯！
Charles.
亲爱的,跟我来吧
My dear. Come with me.
No.
God!
这是个黑暗的年代
We live in an age of darkness.
世界充满恐惧、仇恨和偏见
A world full of fear, hate and intolerance.
不过每个年代,都有人在奋战
But in every age,
there are those who fight against it.
X教授生在一个分裂的世界里
Charles Xavier was born to a world divided.
一个他想治愈的世界
A world he tried to heal.
这是他无法亲自完成的任务
A mission he never saw accomplished.
伟人总是
无法看到自已的目标达成
It seems the destiny of great men
to see their goals unfulfilled.
X教授不只是一位领袖
不只是一位导师,他也是朋友
Charles was more than a leader,
more than a teacher. He was a friend.
当我们恐惧时,他给我们力量
When we were afraid, he gave us strength.
当我们孤独时,他给我们一个家
And when we were alone, he gave us a family.
他也许走了,不过他的教诲
我们、学生们都永远铭记在心
He may be gone, but his teachings
live on through us, his students.
不论我们去哪
都会继承他的理想
Wherever we may go,
we must carry on his vision.
那个理想就是世界和平
And that's a vision of a world united.
幻影猫
Kitty.
巴比?
Bobby.
-你还好吧?
-还好
- You OK?
- Yeah.
只是...教授曾来过我家
It's just... Xavier came to my house.
他说服我来到这里
He was the one that convinced me
to come here.
我也是
Yeah, me too.
-我们都有相同的感受
-不,我们不是
- We're all feeling the same way, you know.
- No, Bobby, we're not.
你有小淘气,而我却...
You have Rogue and I have...
我很想家
You know, I just miss home.
还有冬天的第一场雪
The first snow and all that.
-跟我来
-暴风女要我们留在房里
- Kitty, get up. Come with me.
- Storm told us to stay in our rooms.
不会有人知道的
Don't worry. We won't get caught.
你能穿墙而过,来吧
I mean, you can
walk through walls, you know.
Come on.
这里也可以是你家
This place can be home too.
谢谢你,巴比
Thank you for this, Bobby.
需要送你一程吗?
You need a lift, kid?
No.
你要去哪?
Where are you going?
你不知道惧怕自已能力的感觉
害怕靠近任何人
You don't know what it's like to be afraid of
your powers, afraid to get close to anybody.
我知道
Yeah, I do.
我希望能碰触别人
I want to be able to touch people, Logan.
拥抱、握手
A hug. A handshake.
亲吻
A kiss.
希望你不是
为了某个男人而这么做
I hope you're not doing this for some boy.
听着,如果你想走,那就走吧
Look, if you wanna go, then go.
只是要确定你要的是什么
Just be sure it's what you want.
你不是该叫我留下吗?
Shouldn't you be telling me to stay?
上楼去把行李放下?
To go upstairs and unpack?
我不是你父亲,我是你朋友
I'm not your father. I'm your friend.
想想我刚刚说的话,小淘气
Just think about what I said, Rogue.
我叫玛莉
Marie.
玛莉
还记得我们第一次见面吗?
你知道我在你身上看到了什么?
Remember when we first met? Do you know
what I saw when I looked at you?
我看到下一个阶段的革命
那是我和查而斯梦寐以求的
I saw the next stage in evolution
both Charles and I dreamt of finding.
我想,查而斯为何要将这个女神
变成凡人?
And I thought to myself, "Why would Charles
want to turn this goddess into a mortal?"
我能控制这里面的金属
但是你,你能为所欲为
I can manipulate the metal in this,
but you, you can do anything.
任何你想得到的事
琴
Anything you can think of.
Jean.
够了
Enough.
够了！
你的口气跟他一样
You sound just like him.
他想压制你的能力
Jean, he wanted to hold you back.
-你想要什么?
-我要你做你自已
- What do you want?
- I want you to be what you are.
就如老天的安排
As nature intended.
那种治疗剂的目标是我们全体
我们要自由,就得奋战到底
That cure is meant for all of us.
If we want freedom, we must fight for it.
而这场奋战现在已经展开
And that fight begins now.
她不该跟我们在一起
She shouldn't be here with us.
-她的能力很不稳定
-除非被不对的人控制
- Her power is completely unstable.
- Only in the wrong hands.
-你信任她?她是他们的一份子
-你以前也是
- And you trust her? She's one of them.
- So were you once.
我一直效命于你
如果你让我动手,我早杀了教授
I stuck with you. Would have killed
the professor if you'd given me the chance.
查而斯为变种人付出太多了
Charles Xavier did more for mutants
than you'll ever know.
我最遗憾的
就是他得为我们而死
My single greatest regret
is that he had to die for our dream to live.
-现在呢?我们该做什么?
-查而斯教授创立了学校
So what now? What do we do?
学校也该随他而去
Xavier started this school.
Perhaps it's best that it end with him.
-我们会叫学生们回家
-我们大多都无处可去
- We'll tell the students they're going home.
- Most of us don't have anywhere to go.
我真不敢相信
我们就这么放弃
I can't believe this. I can't believe
we're not going to fight for this school.
我知道现在时机不大对
I'm sorry. I know this is a bad time.
我听说这里是变种人的庇护所
I was told that this was
a safe place for mutants.
以前是的,孩子
It was, son.
现在也还是
我们会帮你找个房间
And it still is. We'll find you a room.
告诉学生们,学校继续开放
Hank, tell all the students
the school stays open.
小淘气?小淘气
Rogue.
Hey, Rogue.
-钢人?你有看见小淘气吗?
-她离开了
- Hey, Pete. Have you seen Rogue?
- Yeah, she took off.
Logan.
- Logan.
- Jean?
罗根、罗根、罗根
你听得见我吗?我在哪里?
Logan. Where am l? Logan.
Logan. Logan.
罗根、罗根
别这样
- Logan.
- Stop.
Logan. Logan. Logan.
-你要去哪?
-你想呢?
- Where are you going?
- Where do you think?
-她走了,她不会回来了
-这点很难说
- She's gone, Logan. She's not coming back.
- You don't know that.
她杀了教授
She killed the professor.
那不是琴
我认识的琴还在里面
It wasn't Jean.
The Jean I know is still in there.
-走开
-听着,你为何不能看清事实
Listen, why can't you see the truth?
-为什么不忘了她?
-因为,因为...
- Why can't you just let her go?
- Because... because...
因为你爱她
Because you love her.
她做了选择,我们也要做出选择
若你支持我们,就留在我们这边
She made her choice.
Now it's time we make ours.
So if you're with us, then be with us.
X学校
培养天才少年
我们不需要治疗！
不需要治疗！
We don't need a cure! We don't need a cure!
想治疗好然后回爸妈身边?
Getting the cure so you can go back home
to mommy and daddy?
我在找人
I'm looking for someone.
我懂了,你的马子
Oh, I get it. Your girlfriend.
我就知道她想治疗
她真可悲
I figured she'd want the cure. She's pathetic.
来啊,冰人
Come on, lceman.
动手啊
Make a move.
还是那个老巴比
还是害怕战斗
Same old Bobby. Still afraid of a fight.
今天的攻击只是第一波
Today's attack was only our first salvo.
只要治疗剂存在
我们就会继续战斗
So long as the cure exists, our war will rage.
你们的城市将不再安全,街头
也不再安全,连你也不安全了
Your cities will not be safe. Your streets
will not be safe. You will not be safe.
至于我的变种人同胞
我请你们
And to my fellow mutants,
I make you this offer...
加入我们,不然就别挡路
Join us or stay out of our way.
已经有太多变种人牺牲了
Enough mutant blood
has been spilled already.
我们正在设法追踪他
We're trying to track them, sir.
We're working hard.
-我们不能让他为所欲为
-我同意
- We cannot let him do this.
- You know I agree, sir.
事关国家安全
关闭沃辛实验室
This is now a national security matter.
Seize and secure Worthington Labs.
我要军队
配备装有治疗剂的枪
I want troops armed with cure weapons
deployed immediately.
崔斯克,找出万磁王并阻止他
运用任何必要手段
And Trask, you have to find Magneto
and stop him by any means necessary.
万磁王想开战,我们就开战
Magneto wants a war. We'll give him one.
快！继续前进！
Let's go. Keep it moving.
缴回旧式武器,缴回所有金属
Turn in your old weapon. Turn in all metal.
刺刀、弹药、识别牌
Bayonets, magazines, dog tags.
领取塑胶武器
领取治疗剂填装弹匣
Pick up your plastic weapons.
Pick up your cure cartridge.
绝对不能带任何金属
Absolutely no metal.
我们不需要治疗剂！
We don't need a cure! We don't need a cure!
向治疗剂说不
同志们,他们想治疗我们
但我告诉你们我们就是治疗剂
They wish to cure us.
But I say to you we are the cure.
治疗衰弱无能的人类
The cure for that infirm, imperfect condition
called homo sapiens.
他们有他们的武器
They have their weapons.
我们有我们的
We have ours.
我们会以前所未见的愤怒力量
袭击这个世界
We will strike with a vengeance and a fury
that this world has never witnessed.
有任何变种人阻挡我们
我们就用这种毒药对付他们
And if any mutants stand in our way,
we will use this poison against them.
我们要去恶魔岛
控制治疗剂,摧毁它的源头
We shall go to Alcatraz lsland,
take control of the cure,
and destroy its source.
之后我们将无人能挡！
And then nothing can stop us.
Jean.
我大老远就闻到你的臭钢味
I know the smell of your adamantium
from a mile away.
-我不是来找你打架的
-聪明的小子
- I didn't come here to fight you.
- Smart boy.
-我是为琴而来
-你以为她不是自愿待在这里的?
- I came for Jean.
- You think I'm keeping her against her will?
-她在这里是因为她想来
-你不知道你面对的是什么
- She's here because she wants to be.
- You don't know what you're dealing with.
我知道
我看过她怎么对付查而斯
I know full well.
I saw what she did to Charles.
而你却眼睁睁的看他丧命?
And you stood there and let him die?
-没有她,我不会走
-你非走不可
- I'm not leaving here without her.
- Yes, you are.
OK.
好,两分钟后会合
Two minutes till rendezvous, Mr. President.
我们有万磁王基地的卫星影像
We have a satellite feed
of Magneto's base of operations.
-怎么找到的?
-她给了我们一切资讯,还有更多
- How did we find it?
- She gave us everything we wanted.
被抛弃的女人的怒火真吓人
Hell hath no fury like a woman scorned.
直接接近前方目标
Approaching target dead ahead.
准备360度袭击
Set for 360-degree incursion.
队长呼叫一号小队
我们随时准备出击
This is Team Leader to Bravo One.
We are green to go.
好,开始攻击
OK, send them in.
OK.
不准动,变种人！
举起双手！
Freeze, mutants!
Get your hands in the air! Hands in the air!
好啦,我投降
OK. I give up.
这是诱饵,部长
Sorry, Mr. Secretary, it was a decoy.
他若不在那里,会在哪里?
If he's not there, then where the hell is he?
沃辛实验室,是开端也是结束
Worthington Labs. It ends where it began.
-你确定那孩子在里面?
-百分之百确定
- Are you sure the boy is still inside?
- 100%.
我们该怎么过去?
我不会游泳
So how are we supposed to get there?
'Cause I don't swim.
交给我吧
Leave that to me.
Storm. Storm.
暴风女、暴风女
你在这里做什么?
What are you doing back here?
我需要帮忙
I need help.
-你找到她了
-她跟万磁王在一起
- You found her.
- Yeah. She's with Magneto.
-他们在哪里?
-我知道他们要去哪里
- Where are they?
- On the move. I know where they're going.
-你看到万磁王了?
-得走了,他们要攻击恶魔岛
- You're saying you saw Magneto?
- We gotta go. They're gonna attack Alcatraz.
-岛上有军队
-那不足以阻止他
- There are troops stationed on that island.
- Not enough to stop him.
着装吧
Let's suit up.
-这以前穿还很合身
-万磁王拿到针剂就所向无敌了
- Hard to believe this once fit me.
- If Magneto gets that cure, we can't stop him.
-他有多少人?
-一支军队,还有琴
- Can you estimate how many he has?
- An army. And Jean.
-他的能力有限,她可不然
-我们只有六个人
- His powers have limits, hers do not.
- There's only six of us, Logan.
对,我们人单势薄
Yeah. We're outnumbered.
我不会骗你
I'm not gonna lie to you.
不过我们失去了史考特
But we lost Scott.
失去了教授
We lost the professor.
一旦放弃
一切就会随他们而去
If we don't fight now,
everything they stood for will die with them.
我不打算让那情况发生
I'm not gonna let that happen.
你呢?
Are you?
那么我们就齐心协力
Then we stand together.
X战警
X-Men.
我们全体
All of us.
我们加入
We're in.
我们走吧
Let's go.
-他们准备好了
-我知道
- They're ready.
- Yeah, I know.
不过你准备好
采取必要手段了?
But are you ready to do what you need to do
when the time comes?
爸,怎么回事?
Dad, what's going on?
地震！
It's an earthquake.
我们被困住了
We're trapped.
查而斯一直想建立沟通的桥梁
Charles always wanted to build bridges.
我的老天
My God.
撤退！撤退！
Fall back! Take cover! Fall back!
那孩子在东南方的角落
The boy's in the southeast corner
of the building.
-好极了
-摧毁它
- Well, then.
- Let's take it down!
下棋时,小卒先走
In chess, the pawns go first.
人类和他们的枪
Humans and their guns.
塑胶的,他们学会了
Plastic. They've learned.
所以才要派小卒先上
That's why the pawns go first.
瞄准桥
Target the bridge.
发射
Fire!
震波女,用震波
瞄准那些武器
Arclight, use your shockwaves.
Target those weapons.
-我的老天爷
-进入隐形模式
- Oh, my stars and garters.
- Go into stealth mode.
-战斗机呢?坦克呢?
-万磁王会把它们压碎
- What about jets? Tanks?
- Against Magneto? He'll turn them inside out.
-地面部队呢?
-离该处有30分钟远
- Where are our ground troops?
- 30 minutes away.
愿上帝帮助我们
Then God help us.
他们来找他了
They're coming for him.
不准你再那么做了
Don't ever do that again.
要你的手下保护大门
You men cover the doors!
大家过来！守住战线！
Everybody get together! And hold this line!
自以为代表正义的叛徒
Traitors to their own cause.
解决他们
Finish them!
还没
Not yet.
去里面找到那男孩,杀了他
Go inside and get the boy. And kill him.
我很乐意
With pleasure.
等一等！
Hold it!
他要去找那个男孩
He's going for the boy!
只要我先到就行了
Not if I get there first.
Kitty!
幻影猫,来啊！
Come on.
把那些也长回来吧
Grow those back.
你不知道我是谁吗?
Don't you know who I am?
我是红坦克,贱人
I'm the Juggernaut, bitch.
要去哪里?
Going somewhere?
-是你发明了治疗剂吧?
-是的
You're the guy that invented the cure, right?
Yes, I am.
小姐们?
Girls.
不！别伤害他！
No. Don't. Don't hurt him.
放开我,这不关我的事
- No. Don't hurt him.
- Let go of me. I didn't do anything.
冷静点
Calm down. Calm down.
不会有事的
Everything's gonna be OK.
-我以为你是外交官
-邱吉而说过,该来的...
- I thought you were a diplomat.
- As Churchill said, "There comes a time..."
啊,你懂我意思
Oh, you get the point.
不！求求你,不要！
Oh, no. Please, no, no, don't.
No.
别害怕
我是来帮你的,我们快出去
No, don't worry. I'm here to help you.
I'm going to get you out of here.
这边
This way.
-怎么回事?
-你的超能力在我周遭会失效
- Oh, my God. What's going on?
- Your powers won't work with me.
跟紧一点,好吗?
- Stay close, all right?
- OK.
I'm the wrong guy to play hide-and-seek with.
-别想跟我玩躲猫猫
-谁在躲了?你这个猪头！
Who's hiding, dickhead?
Don't. No.
不要！不要！
Don't.
别这样！我只是想帮你们！
Please, don't do this.
I only wanted to help you people.
我们看起来像需要帮忙吗?
Do we look like we need your help?
It's time to end this war.
该结束这场战争了
快找掩护
Take cover.
Get out of the way.
躲开
-走吧
-赶快
- Let's go, let's go.
- Move.
Go! Go! Go!
快呀
我们要团队合作
We work as a team.
攻击是最佳防守
Best defense is a good offence.
巴比
你能搞定你的老友吗?
Bobby, think you can take out
your old friend?
Go ahead.
上吧
暴风女,我们需要掩护
Storm, we're gonna need some cover.
Right.
好
你的能力太差了
You're in over your head, Bobby.
你该回学校去
Maybe you should go back to school.
你不该离开学校的
You never should have left.
This is it.
时机到了
Hey.
投个好球吧
Make it a strike.
你永远学不会,对吧?
You never learn, do you?
其实...我学会了
Actually, I do.
I'm...
我...
One of them?
跟他们一样?
这就是他们的阴谋
This is what they want for all of us.
It's over, Jean.
一切都结束了,琴
It's over.
结束了
No! Don't shoot!
别开枪
No!
大家快离开这里
Everybody get out of there!
Bobby!
What have I done?
我做了什么?
我是唯一能阻止她的人
让大家到安全的地方
I'm the only one who can stop her.
Get everyone to safety.
快去！
Go.
Jean!
琴！琴！
我知道你还在里面
I know you're still there!
你宁可为他们而死?
You would die for them?
No, not for them.
不,不是为他们
For you.
而是为你
为你
Save me.
救我
I love you.
我爱你
琴葛蕾
史考特
你回来了?
You're back.
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
I had to.
我一定要去
-这不是我想要的
-我知道
- This isn't what I wanted.
- I know.
这是我想要的
It's what I want.
Hey.
很高兴见到你,孩子
Good to see you, buddy.
With the thanks of a grateful nation
怀着满心的感激
我在此介绍新的联合国大使
I introduce our new ambassador
to the United Nations,
代表全美国公民、人类和变种人
向世界发声
and the representative to the world
for all United States citizens,
human and mutant alike,
Dr. Hank McCoy.
亨利麦寇博士
干得好,毛球
Way to go, fur ball.
Morning.
早安
你好,莫拉
Hello, Moira.
Charles.
查而斯
Visiontext Subtitles: Simon Campbell